This is Dr. Palmer. I am
recording a presentation
on cardiac prevention and
improving communication.
You can reach out to me by my
email, wpalmer at nyit.edu.
Our objectives are to
discuss prevention as they go
to cardiac risk factors,
what you may find in the
history and physical, talk
about some pitfalls in
communication, methods of
documenting risk factors within
your assessment, as well as
the plan and addressing it
in the plan, discuss the
roles of communication written
and verbal you need to
be able to express your
decision-making in your
documentation and oral presentations
such as in your future
third or fourth year
rotations so let's get
started so let's lead off with
prevention we have primary
secondary and tertiary primary
prevention is you know
we don't have a diagnosis
we are talking about some
things that may lead to a
diagnosis such as addressing
poor diet and activity
tobacco use you know we
get spoiled a lot of times
because people come in and
they get their blood pressure
checked but sometimes
primary prevention could just
be checking a person who
doesn't go to the doctor and
just checking their blood
pressure if they do not
have high blood pressure at
the time then you may want
to address their poor diet
their physical activity or
their tobacco use as a
goal of primary prevention
secondary prevention is
we're identifying diseases in
the earliest stages so
we've had two readings of
elevated blood pressure we've
checked their cholesterol
and they have high cholesterol
and we are trying to
address those before they
get other signs or symptoms
such as a stroke or heart
attack so treating their
blood pressure through diet
exercise medications same
with hyperlipidemia before
they've gone on to have a
stroke and heart attack. And
now in tertiary prevention,
we're trying to prevent
them from having another.
So I have a question here.
It is, there's not an
answer per se. It's just
meant to make you think.
55-year-old asymptomatic black
male presents to the clinic.
The patient's concerned
that his brother recently
had a heart attack at age
57, denies any symptoms of
chest pain, palpitations,
dyspnea, nor syncope. His
father had heart disease
and passed away in his 60s.
He does not smoke. His BMI
is 38. His blood pressure
is 140 over 90. And after
completing your history
and physical exam, how would
you end this encounter?
So we take all this
information and now he has
to think about what we're
going to do with it.
So we could recommend that
he lose weight. We could
recommend that he should
eat a healthy diet.
Generally speaking,
there's nothing wrong
with saying that, but
it's not very specific.
Assess other
cardiac risk factors
including glucose
and cholesterol.
Probably a good idea.
We should advise
him that he should
exercise more.
Okay again that may go up
there with number A and B.
Advise him that his
it is genetics and
there's nothing he can
do but take medicines.
Would not be what I would
recommend. But you see
here that there's somewhat
of a right answer in
here, and a lot of them
sound like a good idea.
So what we're going to
do here the rest of this
presentation is talk
about how to refine those
topics and how to address
them in an encounter.
So let's identify cardiovascular
risk factors. I've
also kind of labeled here
where you may find them
during the encounter,
whether you're taking history
or physical exam. So your
first degree relatives with
cardiovascular disease, and
so that's the importance
of why we want you to
take a family history you
find those risk factors
within that tobacco and excess
excessive alcohol use that's
found in social history
physical inactivities also
as well as the diet being
not BMI and central obesity
that's found on the vitals
and also on your exam
you can see that based on
their general appearance
hypertension is also found
in the vitals so even
when you see that first
face sheet and you see
their vitals you can make
determinations based on
what their risk factors
are before you've even
seen the patient dyslipidemia
is ordered in labs
as well as evaluating
for diabetes and fasting
glucose presence of
therosclerosis or existing
cardiovascular disease that's
also found in diagnostics
like imaging tests on
exam as well sometimes
so let's we're going to
talk about some of these
more specifically so
family history first degree
relative risk here is
men prior to age of 55
and women prior to age
of 65 and you know got
some questions here to
thank you know patients
do they understand what
first degree relative is
parents siblings
children for your
typical first degree relatives
When we talk about
the ages up here, men
prior to age of 55, so
it's important to put
that documentation of
what the age was. So my
father had a heart
attack at 90 is different
than my father had a
heart attack at 45.
High blood pressure.
So there's recommendations
that you can find from
the United States Preventive
Services Task Force.
There's variations on
these screenings and
they'll reword them
between different groups.
This is the statement
that I am using here.
Generally speaking, adults
over the age of 18 are going
to get their blood pressure
checked, so when you're
looking at prevention and
identification, generally we
need to be doing every three
to five years if you don't
have any medical conditions,
but people, a lot of
people go to the doctor a
lot, so they get their blood
pressure checked every year,
for every office visit, sick
visit, and such, so we get
a lot more of these than
at prevention here
we're talking about
people who don't
go to the doctor.
If you have risk factors
then yeah they should be
screened every year up from
18 up to adult and if they
are over 40 then they should
be screened every year.
So let's talk about question
two. 46 year old male
diabetic returns to the clinic
for follow-up on elevated
blood pressure. You have
previously counseled the
patient on improving their
diet, increasing aerobic
exercise, and weight loss.
Over the last month the
patient has managed to lose
five pounds and the blood
pressure has lowered from
160 of 100 to 135 over
90 today which is the next
step we could start blood
pressure medicine since
diastolic is 90 and lifestyle
modification has failed
now those that's words i
wouldn't agree that it has
failed it has improved but
also starting blood pressure
medicine isn't necessarily
an unreasonable expectation
here continue current
plan since the stolic
is less than 40 that may
also be reasonable depending
on how much weight they
have to lose. Maybe they do
have more weight that they
could lose and could get
a lower blood pressure
reading. We could evaluate
and modify the current plan
to achieve a better goal.
And again here, you know,
specifically stated
what our goal is.
We could recommend
the carnivore diet.
You know, earlier we
were talking about, you
know, recommending diet
or weight loss. And again,
here is a named diet.
Is this a healthy diet?
Is this what we would
recommend them to do?
I would not recommend
the carnivore diet.
Encourage tobacco use
as it will suppress the
appetite. And that's
really just not an answer.
It, we would never, we
would never recommend
a risk factor to improve
another risk factor.
So, we're going to talk
through this as a case.
We've kind of introduced
you to some of these
considerations, and we're
going to start with a
fictitious patient, Danny
Thomas, date of birth
is 5-15-60. His chief
complaint is chest pain,
vitals, blood pressure 140 over
90, heart rate 82,
respiration 18,
pulse hox 98%, and BMI of
26. And again, this is a
standard door note, something
you'll see in patient
encounters, even in the ICC
or in real-world rotations.
So, we can think about
things before we even get
started. So, what can we
identify? We can get his age,
his vitals, his cheek
complaint. We can think about
possible risk factors that
the patient could have.
You should have a kind
of a preparation of how
you're going to navigate
your history and physical
exam. Make sure that as
we're preparing this,
that you've established
a routine, and especially
for this year, that's your
goal, is to understand
that details are important
and start processing
what details you need to
obtain and set yourself
up to be successful by
having organization.
So, reminder of written
documentation purpose, where,
again, we're communicating,
billing, legal communication.
People are going to be
looking at your notes,
and they need to understand,
you know, if there are
other hospital providers or
groups such as, like, you
know, physical therapy,
respiratory therapy, nursing.
They need to understand
what you're doing and
what your plan is and
what you've done. In the
clinic, very well, you're
running communication to
yourself so you know what
you did last time and
what you were planning
on doing this next time.
Sometimes we also have written
communication for the
patient to take home
so they understand
what is going on.
Billing and insurance
companies will want to look at
evidence of what you're
doing that you've documented
enough to support your
efforts and that you don't
commit fraud. legal as
well, that, you know, if you
are to get sued, then you
have evidence to support
how you address the patient's
illnesses and concerns.
So here's an example of
an HPI, some notes. I
wrote some things. You
know, I chose not to
write the patient's
name because it's on the
door note. It's on the
chart. I did write 65
years old, so I can
remember how old they were.
And then I put some of the kind
of the HPI elements on here.
You know, the goal here
is, is one of the things
that I see often is, you
know, you have to, if you're
writing notes, you have
to be able to read your
notes. So some of y'all
may not be able to read my
notes, but as I'm going
to transcribe this into an
HPI and other documentation,
I just need to make sure
that I can read it. If
I'm using any other kind
of chicken scratch, shorthand,
you know, other people
don't have to read this
part. It can be you, but
it needs to be organized.
It needs to be legible.
so that you can read it
so you see i've used some
abbreviations i've used
like an x a positive sign
an increased arrow sign
that's an arrow looking up
so and here is how
i've turned this into
an hpi danny thomas is a 65
year old male who reports
sharp 8 out of 10 left
chest pain that radiates
into the left back it
started at the end of the day
after doing yard work is worse
with breathing and moving
Tylenol gave no relief
and rest helped some he
did not short enough breath
nausea fever and indigestion
and granted if we go back
to that you'll see that
you know i didn't take
notes and complete sentences
and some of this isn't
even what i wrote down but
i remembered it and so give
yourself some credit you'll
remember more than you
realize or think you will
so after we've completed
the HPI it's a good time
to think about our decision
making you know what is
our differential? Is this
cardiac? Is it pulmonary?
Is it muscular skeletal?
What else could it be?
Is there other
valuable information we
need? So let's look
at the rest of the
medical history, the
subjective component.
So here again is
just some samples
of some notes that I wrote.
Some of it may be a little
bit more legible than others.
Again, we need to be
considering organization. Am
I following an organization?
Am I jumping around?
It may, you know, If
you're taking notes in the
ICC and you've got it
all over your page, then
you may not be able to
find the information.
It may delay you and
your ability to document.
So, remember that,
you know, when we
look at pitfalls,
that organization
and the note
documentation matters.
The details matter,
and there's certain
areas where details
are important.
Make sure that you're
using headings and you're
following the organization
that we gave you.
You have to realize that
everyone across the country
has been trained in a
standardized ways of documenting,
and they're looking for that
information to be in the
correct location with an
appropriate heading so that
they can find that information
quickly and reliably.
Allergies must include
the documentation of
medicine allergies as
well as environmental
mental and always
include reaction medicine
allergies are very important
to make sure that you
don't cause harm other
things such as latex food and
pollen could be a component
of presentation and for
instance medical gloves
may have latex in it and
you could potentially cause
a reaction you know there
are certain other allergies
that can cross react
and so it's always important
to put in all those other
allergies early and confirm
if they don't exist.
Tobacco, alcohol,
and drugs of previous
and past use is
always important to
put in there because
it signifies risk.
So you're going to
see in the end, if you
look at one of my
previous samples where
I mentioned the person
that did not smoke,
well that doesn't mean
that they didn't smoke. And
so if you smoked a pack
per day 30 years ago but
you quit 15 years ago,
that's great that they quit
but they still have
risk for cardiovascular
disease based on that tobacco
use so you have to realize
that you know a significant
amount of history
is going to include risk
and people will often tell
you that they don't smoke
and have just quit recently
so here's an here's the
example of my from my notes
of what i um found and
put into an organization
with past medical history
surgical medicines allergies
family history i chose to
use bullet points here.
I hope you can realize
that it's easy to see
and clear to find this
information. It's not
a run-on social history.
I've also used bullet
points. I put specifics
here. Tobacco one
pack per day for 30
years quit 15 years ago.
Alcohol one beer per day
for most of adulthood.
If there's not a
specific then you know
we want specifics
if we can get them.
Denies illicit drug
use, denies formal
exercise. Do you
think that's the
best way to say that?
What if they used
illicit drugs in the past? Do
you think that implies risk? So
the better way to
document that would be
to say that they
denies any previous or
current drug use,
just the same as
we would do with
tobacco and alcohol.
If you notice here I put
denies formal exercise up
here with denies illicit
drugs and so that may make
that harder to find that
information because it
added on to here so
sometimes students will also
put this in a big paragraph
and that information is
there but it does make it
harder for us to read and
find caffeine a cup of
coffee a day diet high salt
and fast food and the
question i want you to i
want to ask it well is this
diet is this a specific
um enough for us is this
is this identifying um so
on the diet we've got to
consider you know whether
the high salt and fast
food is the right way is it
specific enough is it
representative of their diet and
we'll we'll talk more
about that coming up review
of systems remember you
know our minimum is in lcc
is three systems they got
to be in something different
um so cardiac would be
too close here you know
pulmonary symptoms very well
be important but that you
know should be something
that we potentially ask i've
just given some examples
here of some review systems
that could be kind of
related but not necessarily
directly related objective
remember our files and
general parents Those are
things we document all the
time. They let the reader
know what state the patient
was in, were they stable,
unstable, in distress.
Those kinds of
discernments can happen
from the vitals and
general appearance.
Reminder to not use
the word normal. It's
better to use a description
of what normal is.
It's not very defendable.
There are standard
terminology and abbreviations.
So an example here I've given
for objective documentation,
listing up my vitals, and
then general appearance
here, alert, awake, stated,
age, no acute distress.
Oriented times
three, I see a lot of
times students will
use that, and that's
more neuro than just
general appearance.
Remember, even with
oriented times three, are
you actually asking person,
place, and time? And
you can read through here
and see some of the other
examples of documentation
I used for chest wall
and inspection palpation
evaluating the cardiac exam
you know I comment on things
that aren't there like
no wheezes rails or wrong
guy or no murmurs rubs or
gallops not saying that
it's normal not saying the
PMI is normal. You can use
the words not displaced.
So what about labs? Where
do we document labs?
Labs, imaging, EKG that
have already been obtained,
those come in at the end of
your objective. Ones that
you're ordering are coming
in your plan that you don't
have back yet, but if you
have those results, then
you put them at the bottom
of your objective of after
your physical exam so let's
talk about things that
we can order such as
cholesterol recommendations is
screening everyone at the
age of five years again you
know there are different
organizations have different
recommendations again
this is from a primary
prevention that we don't
have them diagnosed as
having high cholesterol
children generally should
have a between 9 and 11
to just make sure that
they don't have familial
hypercholesterolemia.
So there are new
updates from the ACC,
American Heart
Association, on testing
for able lipoprotein
B and lipoprotein A.
Lipoprotein A is used
once as an adult to define
those higher at risk,
maybe due to familial
reasons. Able lipoprotein
B is used in folks that are
maybe already on a
cholesterol medicine, or they
maybe already met their
LDL goals and HDL goals,
but you're concerned for
the risk factors that
maybe they need to have
more aggressive therapy.
The United States
Permanent Services Task
Force has some recommendations
on starting low
to moderate dose statins.
The American Heart
Association also has
some recommendations.
Some of these considerations
here, they do periodically
change. These are the
ones that I'm presenting,
40 to 75 without
a history of CVD.
one or more cardiovascular
risk factors 10-year risk
greater than 10 percent
American Heart Association is
going to recommend considerations
at lower than 10 percent
you're going to see here
that there's ways to evaluate
this any diabetic from 46
to 75 considerations is
to start cholesterol production
and the main recommendation
is going to be the statin
class of medicines if
they already have a theriskolotic
cardiovascular disease
you'll want to start a statin
if their LDL is greater
than 190 it's considered a
high risk so if you look at
low risk consider with
discussion 5 to 7.4 is you know
if there's family history
at their age then yes that's
going to be something that
you'll want to consider.
So there are calculators.
Historically there's been
what was Framingham risk
estimator and then we went
to the ASCVD and I labeled
this as the previous standard
because now it's kind
of evolved into the prevent
ASCVD and it's recommended
to evaluate 10-year risk
running just 30 to 79
on this slide I put some
of the differences that's
changed over this period
between age sex race smoking
history blood pressure
cholesterol history diabetes
medications basically
the prevent removed race
they also looked at the
GFR. Also, where you live,
such as zip code, is something
else that you can add.
So, we've checked
the cholesterol. We
can calculate
cardiovascular risk
based on the Prevent
ASCVD calculator.
We can then assess the
patient. So, we have the cheap
complaint that we have,
but we also have risk
factors that we could also
document in our assessment.
Remember to not forget
your differential
diagnosis with your
chief complaint.
Make sure you put your
number one as number one, and
then you want to give
your rationale so that the
readers can understand your
decision making process.
So when we talk about
risk factors, remember
there's modifiable
risk factors such
as tobacco use, physical
activity, weight,
blood glucose, pressure,
blood pressure, cholesterol,
and diet. These things
are things that you can
counsel on. So that's where
we can put those in our
assessment and then work on
them in our plan as well.
So we have two different
types of assessments. We have
our differential diagnosis.
And so here is chest pain.
So we may put costochondritis
number one, and this
is our rationale. Angina is
our number two, and put our
rationale here. Pleurisy is
our number three, and our
rationale, but we also have
assessments, and so these
things are also true, such
as these risk factors of
hypertension, physical
inactivity, or unhealthy diet.
Our plan lets you
know what you did to
the patient or what
you're going to do to
the patient. It's
also going to help you
state what you've communicated
to the patients along
with their understanding.
One of the things that
happens sometimes during
the second year, students
will do a great job of
explaining things to the
patient, but then they
don't do a very good job of
documenting what they explain
to the patient. On the
flip side, also students
will run out of time in
the ICC encounters and
then are afraid that they
can't put it in their
plan for, say, I wanted to
counsel the patient or I
recommend doing this because
they didn't say it to the
patient. And, you know,
you're learning during this
time. You're working on
your organization, your
clinical decision-making.
It is okay to put in
your plan, I recommend
to do this. Make sure
you're documenting it
clearly that you did not
already recommend it.
So, I recommended
versus I will recommend.
You know, those are
different words, meaning like
I've done this or I'm going
to do it. And it's okay to
say that and to give yourself
credit for your decision
-making processes like,
I would like to do this.
Remember that you can't
put things in your other
components like your physical
exam for, you can't document
things that you would
have wanted to do. You can
only document in your
objective what you did do. But
in your plan, you can say
what you're going to do. So
examples here for diet, you
can give a specific DASH
diet recommendation, and
that is the dietary approach
to stop hypertension. It is
a specific diet that would
be appropriate for someone
who has high blood pressure.
You could say things to
your patients, such as I
recommend that you should increase
your fruits and vegetables
for five servings a day,
or increase low-fat or
fat-free dairy products,
increase whole-grain consumption,
decrease salt intake to
1,500 to 2,300 milligrams
a day. Those are very
specific. Those are defendable.
Other things, such as
the Mediterranean diet
is a specific diet, and
you could also explain
that as well. And so
I'd encourage y'all
to practice in delivering
this information.
So when you document in
the ICC in your future,
don't just say, I
counseled on diet. It's
not specific. It's not
informative to a reader.
It doesn't give understanding
of the patient's
response or exactly
what you recommended.
You could have said,
I recommended you to
eat pizza and drink
beer all the time.
And technically, that
would be counseling
on diet. It would be a
poor diet. It would
not be a healthy diet.
It needs to be a healthy diet.
I want to give you the
tools to be able to
say that I recommend the
patient to eat a diet
based on their
hypertension. I describe the
diet and the patient's
voice understanding.
That's just an example.
Remember, there's
different ways of
counseling. There's
the five A's,
frames, bathe, trans
-theoretical model.
The American Family
Medicine or Family Practice
has a good read on
counseling. I recommend that.
So motivational counseling.
Remember,
you know, patient
may not be willing or
ready to change at this
point. It's like, you
know, would you consider
to stop smoking?
Maybe they're not ready
yet. And so then you could
set up a follow-up. It's
like, why don't we follow
up in like a month and just
see if you're ready yet.
You know, giving the
patient ownership
of the plan is very
well a way to get
them to be more
likely to make change.
While our patient in
this case had quit
smoking, I would have
praised them. So it's
like, you know, that's
a really good thing
you did for your
health to quit smoking.
Here's an example of
what I would recommend
for tobacco cessation. I
recommended the patient
to quit smoking due
to increased risk it
brings her heart, lung
disease, and cancers.
We went over the
options of medications,
patches, cutting
back, counseling.
You know, you want
to make sure that
you're saying your
recommendation is I
recommended for the
patient to quit.
Sometimes people will
be like, I counseled on
smoking and they're going
to cut back. You need
to make sure that you
document your recommendation.
And the recommendation
is to quit smoking.
Physical activity,
I'll give an example
here as well that,
you know, our goal is
not need 150 minutes
per week of aerobic
exercise for cardiovascular
risk reduction.
This could be 30
minutes a day, five
days a week,
moderate intensity.
You know, you can give out
the full recommendation,
see how they think that
they can integrate integrate
this into their weekly
activity and schedule. Look
for barriers when they, you
know, maybe pause and say,
well, I don't know. So
look for smaller obtainable
goals. Maybe you can get
them to walk for 10 minutes
and they have time to do
that. It's middle of summer
as I'm recording this in
100 degrees in Arkansas.
And people aren't going
to go out and walk
for 30 minutes in the
heat right now. So
you have to kind of
come up with other ideas
for how they can go
out and get exercise.
Maybe they have a gym
membership that they're
not using, or they
have it in their budget
that they could afford
a gym membership.
Maybe they need to
figure out time.
find a cool place.
OMM, don't just put,
we'll treat with OMM.
Give a specific recommendation,
such as recommend
to treat somatic
dysfunctional with MET.
Make sure that you're,
you know, you have an OMM
documented, so we won't
give you credit if
there's not an osteopathic
structural exam. You have
to document your osteopathic
structural exam in
your physical exam, in
your objective portion,
and then again, dress it
in your documentation.
So, remember, for a
recap here, you know, the
person reading your
notes can be following it
from the bottom, from
the top to the bottom.
and in the subjective you
know they're going to be
looking for partner positive
negatives in the HPI they're
going to be forming their
differential as they
read through it they're
going to be looking for those
history and risk factors
for cardiovascular disease
as they're looking through
your note looking at your
physical exam to see if
there any kind of distress or
any other kind of findings
that you've you found or
didn't find your assessments
should be able to connect
back to the subjective
and objective data so you
should be able draw a line
from your differentials and
your assessment to other
portions of your document
and make sure that if
you're putting something in
your plan is directly
connected to your assessment
so what about
verbal communication
let's close with
especially at this
stage we're going
to have you do
oral presentations
you're also going
to be doing oral
presentations on
rotations in your future
So there are different
forms of this, as
far as handoffs or
presentation, it needs to
be organized. It needs
to be given timely.
If you're talking way too
long or rambling, you may
lose the interest of the
person listening. You have
to realize that your
attending is trying to form a
differential as they're
listening to you. So if they
find things that are missing
that you're not giving,
that they may ask you about
that. or maybe some sort
of hole in your thought
process because they're
also trying to evaluate
you to see how you're doing
with your decision. Maybe
there's a knowledge gap or
something that you didn't
think of at this stage, and
they're trying to help you
learn and process that.
So you've got to realize
that as they're listening
to you, they're trying
to think what the
patient's doing as well
as how good a job he did.
so you know details about
that case is important
sometimes not all details
that you may have done you
have may have obtained during
the history is relevant
some rotations some
attendings you're going to
want you to have more
thorough details than others
they may want to have a
presentation that is full
history such as someone in
the going into the hospital
if it's a person that
you're admitting to a
hospital they want to have
the full history that's
presented if it's a new patient
in the hospital sometimes
in just a clinic where
you're maybe seeing someone
with like ear pain they
don't need to know all
the other details on that
and that's going to be
something that you're going
to learn as you go on and
again when we look at oral
presentations in the second
year we're wanting you
to work on delivering
medical information in an
organized confident manner.
Make sure that you're
labeling your location
system and don't just start
throwing out abbreviations.
Make sure you are
following the organization.
At this stage, I would
encourage you the way
we want you to do a oral
presentation is just to
follow the same organization
as the soap note.
lead off with the name
demographics chief complaint
and the same thing you get
to the objective is make
sure you're giving the
vitals in general appearance
every time and then at the
end you're going to give
what you think the patient
could have what your
primary condition is and
what you recommend so this is
the end hopefully it will
help you be able to navigate
your encounters, consider
risks for cardiovascular
disease as you're learning
about the cardiac system
and pathology during the
semester, and give you
an opportunity to practice
your counseling, inform,
educating your patients,
correctly documenting, as
well as delivering your oral
presentation. Thank you.